<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://robertb.me</id>
    <title>Robert&apos;s Space</title>
    <updated>2020-08-15T11:04:26.273Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://robertb.me"/>
    <link rel="self" href="https://robertb.me/atom.xml"/>
    <subtitle>coding, productivity, college life, etc.</subtitle>
    <logo>https://robertb.me/images/avatar.png</logo>
    <icon>https://robertb.me/favicon.ico</icon>
    <rights>All rights reserved 2020, Robert&apos;s Space</rights>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pomodoro Technique: Why, and How]]></title>
        <id>https://robertb.me/post/pomodoro-technique-why-and-how/</id>
        <link href="https://robertb.me/post/pomodoro-technique-why-and-how/">
        </link>
        <updated>2020-08-09T21:26:21.000Z</updated>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the most valuable &quot;productivity tricks&quot; I learned was the Pomodoro technique. This concept has been discussed over and over by numerous productivity geeks, yet many around me still haven't heard of it. So, here is an introduction.</p>
<h2 id="overworked-exhausted-repeat">Overworked, Exhausted, Repeat</h2>
<p>Before learning this trick, I constantly overwork myself. Sometimes, I did it because I had to finish an assignment before the deadline; other times, it is because I was simply &quot;in the zone&quot;.</p>
<p>As a result, I frequently experienced burnouts. I would feel exhausted, with no motivation to do whatever at hand. Even if I force myself to get some work done, I usually couldn't focus. Ugh.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="1"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/robertchenbao/Pictures/master/uPic/Pomodoro%20%231.png" alt="Pomodoro #1" loading="lazy"></figure>
<h2 id="enter-the-pomodoro-technique">Enter the Pomodoro technique.</h2>
<p>In 2018, I learned about the Pomodoro technique. It is a time-management method developed by Francesco Cirillo. It essentially forces you to switch between focused work and short breaks.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><strong>The Pomodoro Technique® Core Process</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Choose a task you'd like to get done</li>
<li>Set the Pomodoro for 25 minutes</li>
<li>Work on the task  until the Pomodoro rings</li>
<li>When the Pomodoro rings, put a checkmark on a paper</li>
<li>Take a short break</li>
<li>Every 4 pomodoros, take a longer break</li>
</ol>
<p>-- Excerpt from <a href="https://francescocirillo.com/pages/pomodoro-technique">Francesco Cirillo's website</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This method has several benefits. Some people found it helpful for keeping track of how much work is done in a day. I found it extremely helpful for avoiding burnouts.</p>
<figure data-type="image" tabindex="2"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/robertchenbao/Pictures/master/uPic/Pomodoro%20%232.png" alt="Pomodoro #2" loading="lazy"></figure>
<h2 id="what-to-do-during-breaks">What to do during breaks.</h2>
<p>When I first began to use the Pomodoro technique, I didn't quite know what was I supposed to do during breaks. Here are some suggestions for beginners:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stretch. Nowadays, many people have to sit in front of a computer screen for hours, whether it is for coding, reading, or attending zoom lectures. As the time goes by, this'll hurt the back and neck a lot. So, stretches is very useful for many people.</li>
<li>Eat or drink. Fruits and water are great.</li>
<li>Breathe. This one is another great choice for short breaks. Even though you don't have the time for a 10-minute meditation, some deep breaths can help a lot.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>The Pomodoro technique is awesome. It is great for students. It is also a wonderful tool for anyone who wants to get more quality work done (and fewer burnouts).</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
</feed>